Sebastian Klaassen

Resume

450 West Outer Drive
Oak Ridge TN, 37830

⑤ (915)216-6123

⋈ sebastian.klaassen@outlook.com
⑥ https://rcsepp.github.io/
www.linkedin.com/in/sebastian-klaassen-349510101/

Summary

Self-driven Software Engineer with strong research experience in the fields of **parallel programming models**, **heterogeneous computing**, **machine learning**, **computer graphics** and **data visualization**. Skilled in C++ (12 years), C# (10 years) and **Python** (6 years).

Work experience

since 03.2020 **Software Development Engineer II**, Amazon Web Services,

https://aws.amazon.com/, Vancouver, Canada.

Providing on-demand resource allocation for AWS web services to optimize cost and availability through AWS Application Auto Scaling.

04.2018–12.2019 Staff Engineer (Senior Software Engineer), Oak Ridge National Lab,

https://ornl.gov/, Oak Ridge, TN.

- 1) Development of a RESTful web service for MODIS, VIIRS and Daymet data products, serving over 12 million request since its initial release in 2018.
- 2) Automatic detection of roots in minirhizotron images using fully convolutional deep learning networks with TensorFlow.
- 3) Development of a unified DevOps framework for running and monitoring utility scripts at the NASA ORNL Distributed Active Archive Center for Biogeochemical Dynamics.

03.2017–09.2017 Contract Engineer, Allen Institute for Cell Science,

http://www.allencell.org/, (Remote work).

Development of a successor to the Interactive Plotting tool on the Allen Cell web page to ensure interactivity as more cells are added to the dataset. The programmed WebGL based scatter plot outperforms existing client side charting software, by interactively rendering datasets of over a million cells.

05.2015–02.2016 Research Intern, Los Alamos National Lab,

http://lanl.gov/, Los Alamos, NM.

- 1) Development of a data analysis tool for in-situ exploration of large scale image databases. The implemented image viewer allows exploration of image datasets in excess of available graphic memory, by streaming images to the GPU asynchronously.
- 2) Development of an application for interactively designing color maps. The tool gives scientists unprecedented insight into their data by enabling a novel form of data exploration through interactive changes to the colormap.

04.2014–04.2015 **Research Assistant**, *University of Vienna - Research group Visualization and Data Analysis*,

http://cs.univie.ac.at/vda, Vienna, Austria.

Implementation of a novel ray tracing algorithm.

- 2013–2017 Freelance Software Developer.
 - Various software projects Computer games, web apps and desktop applications written in C++, Python, C# and Java Script (see homepage https://rcsepp.github.io/).
- 08.2007 and Intern, International Institute for Applied Systems Analysis,
 - 08.2008 http://www.iiasa.ac.at, Laxenburg, Austria.
 - 1) Preparation of environmental data for database upload.
 - 2) Integration of the JasperReports library into the web interface.

Awards

- 2017 **SMC Data Challenge 2017**, Smokey Mountain Computational Science and Engineering Conference, https://smc-datachallenge.ornl.gov/2017/, **Best Solution**.

 Data mining atomically resolved images for material properties
- 2009 ARGE 3D-CAD Competition, http://www.3d-cad.at, 1st Place.
 3D model and animation of the thesis Automated Guided Vehicle
- 2004 ARGE 3D-CAD Competition, http://www.3d-cad.at, 2nd Place.
 3D model and animation of a recreational vehicle

Publications

- 10.2018 A platform for retrieval, analysis, and visualization of MODIS & VIIRS land products, Shrestha R., Boyer A.G., Vannan S., Klaassen S., McNelis J.J., Thornton M.M., Wilson B.E., October 2018 VIIRS/MODIS Science Team Meeting Poster.
- 01.2018 ColorMoves: Real-time Interactive Colormap Construction for Scientific Visualization, Samsel F., Klaassen S. and Rogers D.H., IEEE computer graphics and applications, IEEE Computer Graphics and Applications, 38(1), pp.20-29.
- 10.2017 Scalability of Modern Scatterplot Visualizations for Large Image Datasets, *Klaassen S.*, Master's thesis.
- 08.2017 **Data Mining Atomically Resolved Images for Material Properties**, *Klaassen S.*, 2017 Smokey Mountain Computational Science and Engineering Conference Poster.
- 06.2016 Solving Communication-Intensive Problems Efficiently Using On-Chip Mesh Interconnection Networks, *Klaassen S.*, 2016 ISC HPC Conference Research Poster.
- 05.2016 Interactive colormapping: Enabling multiple data range and detailed views of ocean salinity, Samsel F., Klaassen S., Petersen M., Turton T.L., Abram G., Rogers D.H. and Ahrens J., In Proceedings of the 2016 CHI Conference Extended Abstracts on Human Factors in Computing Systems (pp. 700-709). ACM.
- 06.2013 Solving Communication-Intensive Problems Efficiently Using On-Chip Mesh Interconnection Networks, *Bachelor's Thesis*.

Education

- 03.2014–10.2017 **MSc in Computer Science Media Informatics**, *University of Vienna*, Vienna. with distinction
- 03.2011–01.2014 BSc in Computer Science Scientific Computing, University of Vienna, Vienna.
 - 06.2009 **Graduation from Technical High School Mechatronics**, Höhere Technische Bundeslehranstalt Wien 10, Vienna, with distinction.
- 10.2012-11.2012 **CS188.1x Artificial Intelligence**, *BerkleyX*, https://www.edx.org.

Open Source Contributions

2018 asyncframes, https://github.com/RcSepp/asyncframes.

A concurrency-by-default programming model based on hierarchical coroutines for scalable parallel programming in Python.

2017 **ExaPlot**, https://github.com/RcSepp/GlobalView.js.

A JavaScript library for rendering scatterplots of very large datasets using WebGL.

Computer skills

Languages C++, C, C#, Python, Visual Basic, JavaScript, Java, NASM, Matlab, R, Perl

Graphics Direct3D, OpenGL, WebGL, Vulkan, Ray Tracing

Web & Data Python Flask, AWS, jQuery, D3.js, SQL, NoSQL

DevOps GIT, GitLab CI/CD, Docker, Elasticsearch, Travis CI, Coveralls

Libraries STL, Boost, TensorFlow, MPI, OpenMP, BLAS, LAPACK, CUDA, LLVM